远鉴字幕组制作
[Visionary] 0day-sub
翻译：我问这瓜保熟么 BoxEr BrookDee 丛林的鱼
钢笔F Sue牧师 FilmCattieDex  Zero Ren paris to colorado
校对：我问这瓜保熟么 william2568
我家商品物美价廉哟
Beautiful items for sale!
提供代写代读服务 普什图语跟达利语都可以
Anything written! Anything read! Pashto and Dari!
我家商品物美价廉哟
Beautiful items for sale!
提供代写代读服务
Anything written. Anything read.
普什图语跟达利语都可以 我家商品物美价廉哟
Pashto and Dari. Beautiful items for sale.
我看家你卖东西给一个女人了 我亲眼看到的
I saw you serve a woman! I saw you with my own eyes!
- 呃 我想我没... - 你就是卖了
- Uh, I really don't think... - You were!
提供代写代读服务
Anything written. Anything read.
普什图语跟达利语都可以 我家商品物美价廉哟
Pashto and Dari. Beautiful items for sale.
帕尔瓦娜
Parvana.
我们家能拿得出手来卖的只有这件了
It's the only thing of value we have left.
我都没穿过 一次都没有
I never wore it. Not even once.
在我们国家 你哪有机会穿这裙子呢？ 帕尔瓦娜
Where would you wear it, Parvana?
- 还是继续学习吧 好不好？ - 好吧 爸爸
- Let's continue your studies. All right? - Yes, Baba.
那好 关于丝绸之路 你了解多少？
Now, what can you tell me about the Silk Road?
丝绸之路
The Silk Road.
爸爸 我记不起丝绸之路的相关知识了
Baba, I can't remember about the Silk Road.
或许我们可以把这当成一个故事来记
Maybe if we think of it like a story.
即使我们一无所有 故事也总能记在心间
Stories remain in our hearts even when all else is gone.
自我们的文明伊始 我们的人民就开始讲故事了
Our people have always told stories, from our very beginning,
那时我们的家乡叫作帕提亚和霍拉桑
when we were Parthia and Khorasan.
我们的家园在兴都库什山脉的利爪下被分成数个部分
A fractured land in the claws of the Hindu Kush mountains,
有北部沙漠那炽烈之眼的灼热
scorched by the fiery eyes of the Northern Deserts,
亦包括那黑白交汇的冰峰之凛冽
black rubble earth against ice peaks.
我们的家园就如一个凶兽的骨架
Our land was the petrified skeleton of a monster.
我们的家园叫阿里亚纳
We were Ariana,
是高尚与荣耀之乡
the land of the noble and honorable.
我们可谓是世界交通的枢纽
We were a pathway to everywhere,
让东西方可互通有无
carrying goods from east to west.
我们研究星象
We studied the stars
在混乱的星空中寻找规律
and began to see order amidst the chaos.
我们的人民中涌现许多科学家 哲学家和故事传唱人
We were scientists, philosophers, and storytellers.
为解答疑惑而探求真知
Questions sought answers and then more questions.
我们开始了解宇宙中我们的位置
We began to see our place in the universe.
但我们处于两个交战国的边境交汇处
But we were at the edges of empires at war with each other,
数千年以来
as borders were defined and redefined...
边境无数次被重新界定
over thousands of years.
无数统治者在此开战 有波斯的居鲁士二世大帝
Of these mighty rulers came Cyrus the Great of Persia.
还有马其顿王国的亚历山大大帝
Then Alexander the Great of Macedon.
有印度的孔雀王朝
There came the Mauryan Empire,
也有成吉思汗的铁骑
Genghis Khan,
还有好多好多
and so on and so on.
每次战争都血流成河
Each time there was bloodshed,
而每次战争也都会有幸存者
and each time there were survivors.
历史的轨迹不断地重复着
A pattern repeating itself endlessly.
帕尔瓦娜 我年轻的时候
When I was young, Parvana,
在这个城市里 我体验过和平的滋味
I knew what peace felt like, here in this city.
孩子们都会去读书 女人们也能上大学
Children went to school, women went to university.
这里成了世外桃源
All the empires forgot about us,
至少有那么一段时间是
for a while at least.
但好景不长
But it did not last.
我们的国土变得脆弱不堪
The ground became weak under our feet,
从未安定
always uncertain.
先是一场政变 又来了一次入侵
First came a coup d'état, then an invasion,
之后就是内战
then a civil war.
如此的混乱局面下
In the chaos,
有些人希望领袖可以恢复秩序
some looked to those who might restore order.
但那代价实在是太大了
But at a great cost.
我们给女性定下了严格的德行规范
We have determined specific dignity for women!
女人决不能外出 招惹不必要的关注
Women should not go outside and attract unnecessary attention!
如果女人向外人展露自己的容貌 她将受到伊斯兰教法的诅咒
If a woman shows herself, she will be cursed by the Islamic Sharia
永远也别想上天堂
and should never expect to go to heaven.
一切都变了 帕尔瓦娜
Everything changes, Parvana.
记录这些的故事提醒着我们
Stories remind us of that.
帕尔瓦娜 你到底有没有在听啊？
Parvana, were you listening at all?
我在听呢 爸爸
Yes, Baba.
要不你给我讲讲我们游牧民族的祖先
Why don't you tell me about our nomadic ancestors
和他们那些金山的事 好不好？
and their hills of gold?
好吧
Well?
2000年前
- 然后呢？ - 2000年前...
- Yes? - 2,000 years ago...
有一位巴克特里亚王国公主
there was a Bactrian princess
她有一个王冠
who had a crown.
然后呢？
And?
- 然后...- 帕尔瓦娜？
- And... - Parvana?
走开 别碰我的东西
Away. Keep away from my things.
快走 我说快走 你这只蠢狗
Go away. I said go away, you silly dog!
嘿 你 你以为你在干什么？
Hey, you! What do you think you're doing?
这个女孩为什么乱喊？
Why is this girl shouting?
她只是个孩子 她无意引人注目
She is only a child. She meant nothing by it.
她就是在引人注意
She's drawing attention to herself!
她应该待在家里 而不是在市场抛头露面
She should be at home, not displaying herself in the market.
我家除了一个婴儿 没有男孩 我需要她帮我
I have no son at home, except an infant. I need my daughter to help me.
- 站起来 我们跟你说话呢 - 我是个残..
- Stand up when we talk to you. - I am a cr...
我说给我站起来
I said stand up!
- 我认得你 - 是的 伊德瑞斯
- I know you. - Yes, Idrees.
我以前给你上过课 你那时是个好学生
I was your teacher once. You were a good student.
你给我讲那堆没用的东西 浪费了我宝贵的时间
You wasted my time, teaching me things of no worth.
我已加入塔利班 现在是专杀伊斯兰敌人的战士
I have joined the Taliban and now I fight the enemies of Islam.
好吧 如果我也能算是敌人 那真主已经夺走了我的腿来惩罚我的罪
Well, if I am an enemy, then for my sins God has taken my leg.
老头 你敢嘲笑我？
Are you making fun of me, old man?
我在战争中失去了一条腿 那场我们并肩作战的战争
I lost my leg in the war. The war we fought together.
- 她多大了？- 伊德瑞斯
- How old is the girl? - Idrees.
- 她还是个孩子 - 她这岁数已经能嫁人了
- She is a child. - She's old enough to marry.
我也快要讨老婆了
I'll be looking for a wife soon.
她已经许配给别人了
She's already been promised to someone.
她得把自己裹好
Well, she should cover herself properly.
- 或许你该把眼睛从她身上拿开 - 你跟我说什么？
- Maybe you should stop looking at her. - What did you say to me?
我说你把你那双眼睛拿开
I said stop looking at her.
- 我杀了你 - 伊德瑞斯
- I can have you killed! - Idrees.
- 注意你的言辞 - 够了 走吧
- You watch what you say! - That's enough. Come on.
你还好吗？
Are you all right?
我没事 爸爸
Yes, Baba.
不愧是我的好女儿
That's my girl.
我们回家吧
Let's go home now.
帕尔瓦娜？
Parvana?
你跟那男的说我已经许配给别人了
You told that boy I was promised to someone.
我是要结婚了吗？
Am I getting married?
当然不是 你还是个孩子呢
Of course not. You are still a child.
我现在只想让你天天玩耍 讲讲故事就好
I want you playing and telling stories.
我长大了 不愿意讲什么故事了
I'm too old for that now.
长大了就不爱故事了？ 你一直很爱故事啊
Too old for stories? You've always loved stories.
讲故事能有什么用？
What's the use?
我跟你妈妈谈几句 一切都会好起来的
I'll have a word with Mama-jan and we'll sort it all out.
求你别提那裙子的事
Please don't mention the dress.
要不她会唠叨个没完的
Then I'll never hear the end of it.
- 什么没完？ - 没事 妈妈
- The end of what? - Nothing, Mama-jan.
我们不卖帕尔瓦娜的漂亮裙子了
We're not selling Parvana's good dress.
爸爸 我说的不是这个
Baba, that's not what I meant.
我们需要钱 孩子她爸
We need the money, Baba.
这几天市场比较萧条 过一阵就好了
We'll hold off for a bit. I think business will pick up.
如果经济好起来 我们当然不用卖这裙子
If business picks up, then we won't have to sell it, sure.
但是理想很遥远 现实很骨感 我们必须卖掉它
But the sky is far and the earth is hard. We will have to sell it soon.
好吧 那饭前讲个故事如何？
Well, what about a little story before dinner?
这样暂时我们都不会因裙子的事而烦心了
And we'll forget all about dresses for a while.
或许帕尔瓦娜想给我们讲个故事？
Maybe Parvana would like to read something for us?
现在我不想讲 妈妈 我好累
Not right now, Mama-jan. I'm tired.
她跟我说她已经长大了
She's not a child anymore, she tells me.
所以她现在不喜欢故事了
So she doesn't like stories.
别急着当大人 宝贝女儿
Don't be in such a hurry to grow up, my sweet girl.
长大并没你想的那么好
It might not be all that you expect.
我们家没水了 今早你带回来的水不够
We're out of water. You didn't bring enough this morning.
门边不是有半桶水嘛
But there's half a bucket by the door.
我在你这岁数的时候 家里从来没缺过水
When I was young enough to fetch water, the buckets were never empty.
- 嘿 - 你们俩别闹了
- Hey! - Girls, stop it.
如果你不去井里打水的话
Either you go out and get more water after dinner...
你就得给扎西换尿布
or you can wash Zaki's dirty diapers.
你今天怎么样？ - 好多了
- How are you feeling? - Better.
有你在我就好多了
Now that you're here.
要不是你总洗头 也许水不会这么快就用光呢
Maybe if you didn't wash your hair so much, we wouldn't run out so quickly.
- 帕尔瓦娜 - 要尊重你姐姐
- Parvana. - You should have some respect.
你们怎么不吃呢？
Why don't you eat, hmm?
- 吃饱了一切才会好起来 - 好的
- Things always look better when your belly is full. - Yes, Maudar.
扎西 扎西 等我先把你袖子卷好
Zaki, Zaki, wait till I pull up your sleeves.
不要嘛 妈妈
No, Mama-jan.
这样就好啦
There. There you go.
别把葡萄干都吃了 帕尔瓦娜 那是留给扎西的
Don't eat all the raisins, Parvana. Leave them for Zaki.
你怎么不把你下巴上的那粒大葡萄干给扎西呢 苏拉娅？
Why don't you give him that big raisin on your chin, Soraya?
哦 不对 那不是葡萄干
Oh, but it's not a raisin.
是个长毛的大痣
It's a big, hairy mole.
帕尔瓦娜 向苏拉娅道歉
Parvana, apologize to Soraya.
帕尔瓦娜？
Parvana?
他就在里面 我看他进去的
He's in there! I saw him!
- 如果家里有女人... - 爸爸？
- If there are women present... - Baba?
把自己裹好
Cover yourselves now!
就这个人 他是伊斯兰的敌人
That's the man. An enemy of Islam.
他有禁书 还教女人读禁书
He's got forbidden books, and he's teaching the women with them!
- 放过我们吧 - 他什么也没干
- Leave us be! - He's done nothing!
拿孺拉·阿利在 跟我们走一趟吧
Nurullah Alizai, you must come with us.
爸爸
Baba!
- 你们不能带他走 - 爸爸
- You can't take him! - Baba!
爸爸
Baba-jan!
你们要带他去哪？
Where is he being taken?
去监狱
To prison.
普利查西监狱的人会好好教育他的
They'll teach him a good lesson in Pul-e-Charkhi.
爸爸
Baba!
妈妈？ 我能开灯吗？
Mama-jan? Can I light the lamp?
嘘 帕尔瓦娜 你会吵醒扎西的
Hush, Parvana. You'll wake Zaki.
可如果他们放过了爸爸
But if they let Baba go,
他需要灯光才能看到家在哪
he'll need a light in the window to see home.
他怎么可能还回得来？他连他的拐杖都没来得及带走
How could he come home? He doesn't even have his stick to walk with.
快睡觉吧 都会好起来的
Go back to sleep. It will be all right.
你怎么知道的 妈妈？你怎么知道？
How do you know that, Mama-jan? How do you know?
别说了 帕尔瓦娜 妈妈已经够愁的了
Be quiet, Parvana. She has enough to worry about.
嘿 扎西 别拽了
Hey! Zaki, stop it.
起床了 帕尔瓦娜 别闹了
Get up, Parvana. Stop playing around.
为什么？怎么回事？
Why? What's going on?
你跟我去找你爸爸
You and I are going to find Baba.
那个男孩说你爸爸在普利查西监狱 我们今天就去那
The boy said he was being taken to Pul-e-Charkhi prison, so that's where we are going.
但是没有爸爸 我们不能出门
But we can't go outside without Baba.
苏拉娅正在写一封给监狱长的信
Soraya is writing a letter for the prison governor
信中对拿孺拉被捕事件提出抗议并请求立即释放你爸爸
to protest Nurullah's arrest and ask for his release.
至少我能把信给他们 - 妈妈 这是不允许的
- At least I can give them that. - Mama-jan, it's not allowed.
如果不引人注意的话 我们不会有问题的
We might be all right if we don't draw attention to ourselves.
- 但我们不能... - 行了 帕尔瓦娜
- But we can't... - Come on, Parvana.
带上你爸爸的拐杖 准备出发
And bring Baba's walking stick. We have to get going.
妈妈
Mama.
嘿
Hey.
嘿 你
Hey, you!
问安 你能告诉我普利查西监狱是哪个方向吗？
Salaam. Can you tell me the way to Pul-e-Charkhi?
问安 过河后向东走
Salaam. Uh, it's east, past the river.
- 但是路很远 - 谢谢您
- But it's a long way. - Thank you, sir.
听好 你们得从老城穿过去 要不你们会被抓的
Listen. Go through the old town, or you'll be caught.
为什么你们独自在外？
Why are you out here by yourself?
- 你丈夫呢？ - 我没办法啊
- Where is your husband? - I have no choice.
没有成年男性伴随 女人禁止独自出门
It's not permitted to be out here without your husband or your brother.
- 对不起 我知道的 - 你懂吗？
- I'm sorry. I know. - Do you understand?
我带着这封抗议我丈夫的抓捕行为的信...- 别废话 快回家
- I am bringing a letter protesting my husband's arrest... - Just go home.
- 不行 - “不行”是什么意思？
- No! - What do you mean, "no"?
这是我的丈夫 拿孺拉·阿利在
This is Nurullah Alizai, my husband.
- 他在无指控前提下昨晚被捕 - 禁止留照片
- He was arrested last night with no charges laid against him. - Photographs are forbidden!
- 我家里只剩女人了... - 你想干什么？ 又是给我看照片...
- I have no one at home... - What are you doing, showing me a photograph?
- 又是在外抛头露面的 快滚回家 - 我家里只有女人和孩子
- Out here by yourself. Go home! - There is no one in my house except for children.
你不能在外面闲逛 你懂吗？立即回家
You have no business out here. Do you understand? Go home. Immediately.
你这是自找麻烦
You're looking for trouble now!
你是你丈夫和民族的耻辱
You are an insult to your husband, to your race!
我得知道他现在状况如何
I need to find out what happened to him!
闭嘴
Shut up!
去监狱也没什么用
Going to the prison will change nothing.
如果你去监狱惹麻烦
If you make trouble like this,
你丈夫会因你的无礼行为而受重罚的
your husband will be punished severely for your insolence.
如果你再看到你在外不回家的话 我会把你抓起来的
And if I find you out here again by yourself, I will arrest you.
现在回家
Now go.
妈妈？
Mama-jan?
带我回家
Take me home.
- 还要 - 嘘
- More! - Shh.
去打水 帕尔瓦娜 家里没水了
Go get water, Parvana. We have none left.
快去
Come on.
滚出去
Get out!
你想干什么？
What are you up to?
快离开这 他们会看到你的
Get out of here. They'll see you!
嘿 站住
Hey, stop!
听见没 我让你站住
Stop when I tell you!
来这边
Through here!
站住
Stop!
那男孩往哪跑了？
Where did that boy go?
你看到了吗？看到他了吗？
Did you see? Did you see?
- 嘿 那个女孩你别跑 - 嘿
- Hey, you! Girl! - Hey!
- 别跑 - 别管那个女孩了
- Come on! - Forget about her!
帕尔瓦娜 你只打回来半桶水
Parvana, this is only half a bucket.
你不能打满一桶水再回来吗？
Couldn't you fill them up all the way?
扎西 嘘 别吵醒妈妈
Zaki, shh. Don't wake her.
- 嘘 扎西 - 妈妈
- Hush, Zaki. - Mama-jan!
- 嘘 - 哄他安静下来 帕尔瓦娜
- Shh. - Sooth him, Parvana.
妈妈
Mama-jan.
给他讲个故事
Tell him a story.
妈妈...
Mama...
很久很久以前
One time in the distant past,
在兴都库什山脚下有个小村庄
there was a little village at the foot of the Hindu Kush mountains.
- 我想要妈妈 - 嘘 好好听故事
- I want Mama-jan. - Shh. Listen.
村民刚得到许多珍贵的种子
The villagers had just managed to gather precious seeds.
为此 他们载歌载舞 开怀大吃
And so, there was dancing and singing and laughing and eating.
每个人都洋溢着欢乐的笑容
Everyone was happy.
尤其是一个男孩
Especially for one boy
歌 舞 笑 吃 属他最欢
who danced and sang and laughed and ate more than anyone else.
正当村民载歌载舞 开怀大吃的时候
While the villagers were dancing and singing and laughing and eating,
怪物来袭了
monsters were coming.
怪物们吓跑了驴子 啃食了树木
The monsters frightened the donkeys and ate the trees.
他们偷走了全村最宝贵的东西...
They stole the most precious thing in the whole village...
明年用来耕种的种子
the seeds for next year's crop.
然后怪物们跑回其主人栖息的兴都库什山脉...
Then they ran back to the Hindu Kush mountains where their master lay...
它就是可怕的象王 有着像尖刺一样的象牙
the dreadful Elephant King with spikes for tusks.
嗷儿！
Grrrroar!
嗷儿！嗷儿！
Grroar! Grroar!
嗷儿！
Grroar!
妈妈
Mama-jan.
求你快吃吧 妈妈 吃饱了才会好受些
Please eat, Mama-jan. You'll feel better when your belly is full.
我们家快断粮了
There's hardly any food left.
那我去集市
I'll go to the market.
- 问安  - 问安  请给我12个橙子
- Salaam. - Salaam. Twelve oranges, please.
100阿富汗尼
谢谢
Thank you.
问安 请问6个苹果要多少钱？
Salaam. How much for six apples, please?
问安 孩子 我不能卖给你
Salaam, child. I can't serve you.
但是 先生 求你了 能卖给我6个苹果吗？
But, sir, can I please have six apples?
- 让你的爸爸来买吧   - 我爸爸被带走了
- Get your father to buy food for you. - My father has been taken.
对不起 要不你晚点再来买吧
I'm sorry. Maybe come back later.
就那样被偷了 但是你懂的...
Literally stolen. But you know...
问安 我能买1公斤米吗？
Salaam. Can I have a kilo of rice, please?
- 问安  - 嘿 说你呢
- Salaam. - Hey, you!
女孩
Girl!
嘿 站住
Hey, stop!
我让你站住你就站住
Stop when I tell you!
回去 回家去
Go! Go home!
我把包弄丢了
I dropped the bag.
- 嘘  - 我把钱给丢了
- Hush. - I lost the money.
- 头往后仰着  - 但是我还是可以去挑水的
- Keep your head back. - I can get the water though.
现在先别担心这些
Don't worry about that now.
我给你留了一块馕饼
I saved you a piece of naan.
我给你热一下 就会又好吃又新鲜 好不好？
I'll heat it up for you so it's nice and fresh. All right?
- 我们该怎么办？ - 我也不知道
- What are we going to do? - I don't know.
也许明早我早点出去 在市场人多起来之前买吃的回来
Maybe if I go out early, before it's crowded.
没用的 帕尔瓦娜
It won't work, Parvana.
市场里的人不会冒险东西卖给你的
Market sellers won't risk getting in trouble for serving you.
妈妈的表兄住在马扎里沙里夫
Mama-jan has cousins in Mazar-e-Sharif.
我可以写信请他们帮帮忙
I could write to them for help.
但是我们跟他们连面都没见过 你怎么知道他们会帮忙呢？
But we've never even met them. How do you know they will help?
我们现在就需要食物啊
We need food now.
这些是你哥哥的旧衣服
These were your brother's clothes.
它们很大 但是穿的时候向上提一提就好
They will be big, but we can take them up a bit.
我看起来像男孩吗？
Do I look like a boy?
你看起来像苏莱曼
You look like Sulayman.
- 太像了 - 妈妈
- So much like him. - Mama-jan.
他是个好男孩
He was such a good boy.
他那会儿也不比你现在大多少
Not much older than you are now.
嘘
Shh.
没事的 妈妈
It's all right, Mama-jan.
帕尔瓦娜要去集市买食物 还要打水
Parvana is going to the market for food and water.
只有这个办法了 妈妈 我们什么都没有了
It's the only way, Mama-Jan. We have nothing left.
但是这些果汁是温的 我才不要温的果汁
But these juices are warm. I don't want warm juice.
是的 我就是那么说的 但是你知道的...
Yes, that's what I said, but you know...
问安 向您问安
Salaam. Salaam!
打扰下 问安
Excuse me. Salaam!
问安 问安  进来吧 小伙子
Salaam! Salaam! Come inside, boy!
我又不送货 是吧！
I'm not going to deliver, am I?
就是这么回事 你知道了吧？
But you know how it goes, right?
说吧 你要买什么
Well, let's hear it.
我要买一公斤大米 半公斤小扁豆 和一小点葡萄干
I need a kilo of rice, a half kilo of lentils, and a small amount of raisins.
一小点
A small amount?
卖你多少按我的想象来？
Should I go by my imagination?
是的
Yes.
这孩子 不是很灵光啊
Not very bright, this one.
烂铁也造不出利剑啊
Poor iron won't make a sharp sword.
看看他的傻笑
Look at him smiling!
这孩子都不知道我们在取笑他什么
Little guy doesn't even know when he's being made fun of.
谢谢您 非常感谢
Thank you. Thank you very, very much.
茶都洒出来了
You're spilling the tea.
对不起 叔叔
Sorry, Uncle.
你是谁？ 你为什么盯着我看？
Who are you? Why were you staring at me?
- 你叫什么名字？ - 我的名字？
- What is your name? - My name?
- 我在哪见过你的   - 不是... 我不是...
- I know you from somewhere. - No... I wasn't...
- 不是什么？  - 你不可能认识我
- Wasn't what? - You don't know me.
- 我认识你的  - 不可能！
- I do know you. - No!
- 我真认识你 你是帕尔瓦娜   - 我不是
- I do know you! You're Parvana! - I'm not!
我是什沃吉亚 记得吗？ 学校里那个？
I am Shauzia! Remember? From school?
- 什沃吉亚？ - 我之前是留长头发的 话说那会儿你也是
- Shauzia? - I had long hair then, but so did you.
- 德利瓦  - 别跟别人说
- Deliwar. - Don't tell anyone.
给你帽子
Here's your cap.
你需要一个男孩的名字
You need to get a boy's name
这样下次别人再问你的时候 你就不会犹豫了
so you don't hesitate next time somebody asks you.
我现在叫德利瓦
I am Deliwar now.
名字的意思是“勇敢”
It means "brave."
- 你在哪呢？ - 我 我得走了
- Where are you? - I-I have to run.
能见到你真好
It was good to see you.
德利瓦
Deliwar.
妈妈 请坐下吧
Mama-jan, please sit down.
- 马上要到宵禁了 如果到时候她还没有回来呢？ - 她没事的 我...
- It will be curfew soon. What if she's not back by then? - She's fine. I'm...
谁肚子饿了？
Who's hungry?
帕尔瓦娜
Parvana.
感谢真主安拉 他把你给我带回来了
Praise Allah. He has returned you to me.
妈妈 你把馕饼都挤扁了
Mama-jan, you're squashing the naan.
闻起来太香了 帕尔瓦娜
It smells delicious, Parvana.
扎西
Zaki.
是我啊 认出来了么？
It's me. See?
我特别为你买的
I bought them especially for you.
帕尔瓦娜？
Parvana?
如果你现在就跑出去打水
If you run out and get some water,
等你回来时 他就会习惯你的新样子了
he'll get used to you by the time you come back.
- 但是我已经累了 - 快点 帕尔瓦娜
- But I'm tired. - Hurry on, Parvana.
马上就要宵禁了
It's almost curfew.
你看着太像他了
You look so much like him.
去把苏莱曼的衣服换下来吧
Go change Sulayman's clothes,
要不该弄脏了
or you'll get them dirty.
已经脏了
They are already dirty.
大象
Elephant.
什么？
What?
他想让你继续讲大象的故事
He wants you to continue your story about the elephant.
大象
Elephant.
好吧 嗯...
Well, um...
在村子里
in the village,
在兴都库什山脉脚下
under the Hindu Kush mountains,
可怜的村民们都失声痛哭
the poor villagers cried bitter tears.
没有了珍贵的种子 他们变得惊慌失措
They did not know what they would do without their precious bag of seeds.
明年春天没有了种子可以去播种
They would have nothing to sow come next spring
到了冬天也没有可以吃的食物
and nothing to eat come next winter.
但是那个男孩 他并没有哭
But the boy, he did not cry bitter tears.
他看向山峦 然后大喊...
He looked toward the mountain and he shouted...
我才不害怕你呢
I am not afraid of you,
又大又扎人的坏象王！
big, spiky, bad Elephant King!
也许有一点点害怕
Well, maybe he was a little bit afraid.
他告诉村里这些以苦泪洗面的人
He told the villagers who had been weeping bitter tears
在春天之前 他就能把种子拿回来
that he would get the bag of seed back before spring.
在春天到来之前 我就能把种子拿回来
I will get the bag of seed back before spring.
但是他们都嘲笑了他
But they laughed.
他们大笑不止 因他只是个孩子 并不是一位伟大的勇士
They laughed and laughed, because he was a child and not a great warrior.
但是男孩又一次发了誓
Yet the boy repeated his promise.
我说了 我会在春天之前把那一袋种子拿回来
I said, I will get the bag of seed back before spring.
接着他离开了村庄
And he left the village
向着象王的怒吼勇敢前进
to the sound of the Elephant King's roars ahead of him.
吼！
Roar!
妈妈 既然现在我扮成男孩了
Mama-jan, now that I am a boy
我们就可以去监狱找爸爸了
we can go to the prison and find Baba.
不 帕尔瓦娜 我们不能这么做
No, Parvana, we can't do that.
- 为什么不行？ - 嘘 安静
- Why not? - Shh.
没你想得那么简单 帕尔瓦娜
It's not that simple, Parvana.
但我们总得试一试啊
But we have to try.
- 我们什么也做不了  - 才不是
- There's nothing we can do. - That's not true.
别说了 帕尔瓦娜 别惹她伤心了
Stop it, Parvana. You're upsetting her.
嘿 嘿 我叫你站住 你怎么还跑？
Hey! Hey! I told you to stop! Why do you keep running?
别人叫你站住的时候 你就应该乖乖听话
You should have stopped when you were told to.
你的布卡袍呢 你为什么如此打扮就出门
Where's your burqa? Why are you dressed like this outside your house?
我丈夫把我的布卡袍拿走了 我得去买药
My husband took my burqa. I needed to buy medicine.
住嘴
Stop it. Stop it.
他居然允许你出门不穿布卡袍 他该受到惩罚
He should be punished for letting you outside like this!
- 拜托 别这样 - 你必须得替他受罚
- Please, please! Please! - You have to take his punishment!
乖乖待在里面吧 那才是属于你的地方
Stay inside where you belong!
德利瓦 德利瓦
Deliwar. Deliwar!
你想好叫什么了吗？
Well? Have you remembered your name yet?
我想我没法继续扮男孩了
I don't think I can go on like this.
太可惜了 我还指望你帮帮我呢
Too bad. I could use some help.
- 我看到了些事 - 你指望我能说什么？
- I saw something. - What do you want me to say?
我本该帮忙的
I should have helped.
- 你能做的也就是给自己招来几次鞭打了 - 但我不是男孩
- You'd have helped yourself to a good whipping, that's all. - But I'm not a boy.
你不是男孩 也不是女孩
You're not a boy, you're not a girl.
我需要帮助 托盘太重了 你能帮我下吗？
I need a helper because this tray is too heavy. Will you help?
快挠挠我鼻子 如果我松手皮带会断的
Scratch my nose. Quickly. If I let go of the tray, the strap will break.
好多了
That's better.
- 奥狄什 - 你说什么？
- Aatish. - What?
我想好我的名字了 就叫奥狄什
I remembered my name. It's Aatish.
- 那可算不上是个名字 - 它的意思是“火”
- That's not really a name. - It means "fire."
我知道它的意思 不代表这词算是个名字
I know what it means, but it's still not a name.
可它跟我挺配的
Then it suits me fine.
那我就叫你奥狄什好了
I'll call you Aatish then.
如果你是个男孩 你想去哪里都行
When you're a boy you can go anywhere you like,
奥狄什汗
Aatish Khan.
我们要去哪？
Where are we going?
等着瞧吧
You'll see.
如果有人看到我们怎么办？
What if someone sees us?
我一般都假装说我在这工作
I usually just pretend I work here.
假话说道你自己都信了 那别人也会信
If you look like you believe it, then they will too.
看到没 我们就是清洁工
See? We're cleaners.
你还在等什么呢？
What are you waiting for?
我们不拿走的话 就白白便宜给老鼠了
It's either ours, or the mice eat it.
我得想个办法去找我爸爸
I need to find a way to see my Baba.
喜欢的话 把我爸给你都行 反正我不想要他这样的爸爸
You can have mine if you like. I don't want him.
自从我爸入狱后 我们就再也没听到过他的消息了
My father was taken to prison and we've heard nothing of him since.
- 他们是不会让你见他的 帕尔瓦娜 - 但是我现在是个男孩了
- They won't let you see him, Parvana. - But I'm a boy now.
没什么区别 无论他们是继续关着你爸爸还是放了他 你都帮不上什么忙的
Doesn't make a difference. They'll keep him or let him go, but there's nothing you can do.
这可说不准
You don't know that.
抱歉 但事实就是这样
I'm sorry. It's just the way it is.
也许有办法 但是得花上很多钱
There might be a way, but you'll need lots of money.
钱能有什么用？
What for?
靠贿赂能办成很多事 很多很多
You can get a lot done with bribes. A lot.
提供代写代读服务
Anything written. Anything read.
普什图语跟达利语
Pashto and Dari.
我家商品物美价廉哟
Wonderful items for sale.
提供代写代读服务
Anything written! Anything read!
之前在这摆摊的男人呢？
What happened to the man who used to sit here?
这问题很好答吧
It is a simple question.
你难道不知道吗？
Don't you know?
我怎么会知道？回答问题 他在哪？
How should I know? Answer the question. Where is he?
- 他去马扎里沙里夫了 - 那你又是他的什么人？
- He left for Mazar-e-Sharif. - And what are you to him?
我是他的外甥 我叫..奥狄什
I'm his nephew, uh... Aatish.
你认字吗？
Do you know how to read?
- 你有什么要我读的？我会普什图语和达利语 - 读读这个
- Do you have something to read? I read Pashto and Dari. - Read this.
让我见识下你的水平
Let's see if you're any good.
快点 把信拿出来
Come on. Take it out of the envelope.
“亲爱的拉扎克……”
"Dear Razaq..."
大声点 不然我去叫别人读了
Louder, or I will have to take my business elsewhere.
“亲爱的拉扎克 我希望在喀布尔的你能收到这封信
"Dear Razaq, I hope this letter reaches you in Kabul.
我写信给你 是想告知你一个不好的消息
I'm writing to you with sad news.
很遗憾地告诉你 哈拉·贝格姆在去她妹妹婚礼的路上去世了
I am sorry to tell you that Hala Begum died on the way to her sister's wedding.
她坐的那辆巴士碰到了地雷
The bus she was traveling on hit a land mine.
她受了重伤 难以救治
Her injuries were too great to bear
几小时之后便去世了
and she died some hours afterward.
我知道这对你来说必定是天大的打击
I know this must be a great shock to you,
但我要跟你说 在我最后一次和哈拉的谈话中
but please know that when I last spoke to Hala,
她告诉我说你对她真的很好
she told me of your kindness toward her.
愿真主安拉保佑你
May Allah bless you now,
指引你道路 给予你勇气”
guide your path, and give you courage."
节哀顺变
I'm sorry.
我亲爱的宝贝
Ah, there's my sweet little girl
脸上全是喀布尔的灰尘
underneath all the dust of Kabul.
帕尔瓦娜 你给扎西什么了？
Parvana, what did you give Zaki?
- 1块糖 - 1整块？
- It's a piece of candy. - A piece?
喔
Oh!
太大了 他噎着了
It's big enough to choke him!
他没事的 苏拉娅 你坏他兴子呢
Let him be, Soraya. You're spoiling his fun.
嗷
Ow!
继续讲吧 帕尔瓦娜
Continue the story, Parvana.
讲给扎西听
For Zaki.
很久很久以前 有一位年轻的小男孩
There was this young boy,
他向村民发誓 要去找到那袋珍贵的种子
and he promised his people to find the precious seeds.
那大象呢 大象呢？
Elephant? Elephant?
对 还有那头大象
Yes, and the elephant.
晚上 男孩漫步穿过松林
At night, the boy walked through the pine trees
准备去山里跟象王对峙
on his way to the mountain to face the Elephant King.
在黑暗中 有个东西在跟着他
Something was following him in the darkness,
但他太害怕了 不敢回头看看到底是什么
but he was too terrified to turn around and face it.
于是他开始跑
He began to run,
跟着他的那东西也开始跑
and the thing that chased him also ran.
男孩跑得越快 那东西追得更紧
The boy ran faster and so did his pursuer.
他就在黑夜里奔跑
He ran into the night,
未知的魔鬼追逐着他 直到他再也没有力气继续跑
chased by the unknown demons until he could run no more.
他从山坡上摔了下去
He tumbled down a hill.
一直向下摔
Down.
向下摔
向下
Down.
亲爱的表兄 我们已很多年没有联系了
Dear Cousin, it has been many years since we have spoken,
我写这封信是想告诉你 我丈夫被抓了
but I am writing to you now to tell you that my husband has been arrested
他何时会被释放 能否被释放 我们都不得而知
and we have no word on when he will be released, if at all.
我们一家都很绝望 我急需你的帮助
My family is in a desperate situation and I need your help.
我家长女已到了可以嫁人的年龄了
My eldest daughter is now of age,
我希望你能考虑让她嫁给你最年幼的儿子阿杰玛
and I am asking that you consider her as a bride for your youngest son, Ajmal.
请把我们带出喀布尔
Please take us out of Kabul
这样我们才有生存下去机会
so that we may have a chance of survival.
我们不会成为负担的
We will not be a burden to you.
我们有生活技艺 也很坚强
We are skilled and strong
你在我们身上也不会有太多的花销
and need little by the way of means.
愿真主安拉保佑你 费特马
May the blessings of Allah be upon you. Fattema.
提供代写代读服务
Anything written! Anything read!
Anything written!
这裙子多少钱？
How much for the dress?
问安 这裙子是手工缝制的
Salaam. It's handmade.
- 多少钱？ - 3000
- How much? - 3,000.
别想唬我 我出300
Don't be stupid. I'll give you 300.
这可是产自马扎里沙里夫的手工制品哦
Handmade in Mazar-e-Sharif.
您的女儿穿上这么漂亮的裙子 一定会很开心的
Your daughter will be very happy to wear such a beautiful dress.
她是我的妻子
She is my wife.
1500吧
看这裙子卟呤卟呤的 多闪啊
See how it sparkles?
我给你1000
Here's 1,000.
- 你挣了多少钱？ 1000
- How much did you make? - A thousand.
这钱差不多够贿赂一次了
That might be enough for a good bribe.
- 真的？ - 当然了
- Really? - Definitely.
我也在攒钱 只要是能从我爸那瞒下来的钱 我都会存起来
I'm saving up too. Whatever money I can hide from my father, I keep.
慢慢积少成多
And it's mounting up to a nice little sum.
看见了吗？
See?
你知道的 我可不想一直都呆在这
I'm not going to stay here forever, you know.
- 你见过海吗？ - 没有
- Have you ever been to the sea? - No.
我也是
Neither have I.
但是我听说过月亮会把海水都牵引到海岸上
But I've heard that the moon pulls the water onto the shore
然后海水又会退回去
and then back out again.
我想去看看
I want to see that.
我想把脚放在温暖的沙滩上 感受上涨时海水击打的凉意
I want to put my feet on the warm sand and have them cooled by the lapping water.
你爸爸呢？他不指望你养活吗？
What about your father? Doesn't he depend on you?
我是个好儿子
I am a good son.
但他可不是个好爸爸
But he is not a good father.
如果你在海边 你会干什么？
What will you do by the sea?
做些小买卖 跟现在差不多 不过是为了我自己
I'd buy things and sell things, like I do here, but for myself.
有的人去海边 什么事情也不做
There are people who go to the edge of the water to do nothing.
他们只是戴着墨镜坐在那里看海
They just sit there and they look at the sea with their sunglasses on
或带着游泳圈游泳
or swim about on floating tubes.
那我可以向他们卖这些东西
So I could sell them those things.
听起来是个好主意啊 德利瓦
Hmm. That sounds nice, Deliwar.
也许我们可以合伙
And maybe I'll join you.
- 你想要去哪？ - 祝我好运吧
- Where are you going? - Wish me luck.
- 你怎么回来这么早？ - 我给扎西带了一些面包和葡萄干
- Why are you back so early? - I have brought some bread and raisins for Zaki.
你想做什么 帕尔瓦娜？
What are you doing, Parvana?
我要去找爸爸
I'm going to find Baba.
- 不行 你不能去  - 我必须去
- No, you're not. - I'm going.
宵禁之前你是赶不回来的
You won't make it home before curfew.
我一定要去 你阻止不了我
I'm going. There's nothing you can do to stop me.
妈妈已经很受罪了 你别做蠢事来雪上加霜了
Mama-jan has been through enough without you doing something so stupid.
- 我必须找到爸爸  - 帕尔瓦娜
- I have to find him. - Parvana!
帕尔瓦娜
Parvana!
有人吗？
Excuse me.
问安 有人吗？
Salaam. Hello!
有人吗？
Excuse me!
你想怎样？
What do you want?
- 我说了 你想怎样？  - 我想见见我爸爸
- I said, what do you want? - I want to see my father.
- 谁？  - 我的爸爸 拿孺拉·阿利在
- Who? - My father, Nurullah Alizai.
两个星期前无故被带到这里
Brought here two weeks ago without charge.
- 滚开   - 我有钱......1000阿富汗尼
- Get out of here. - I have money... 1,000 afghani.
- 如果你答应帮助我 钱就归你  - 嘿 你在干什么？
- I can give it to you if you promise to help. - Hey, what are you doing?
没事 只是在赶个孩子走
Nothing. Just getting rid of a kid.
求你了 开门吧
Please! Open up!
我要见我爸爸 我要见他
I have to see my father! I have to see him!
不想挨更多揍就快滚
Now get out of here unless you want some more.
人们说有时雷声大雨点却小
They say it doesn't always rain the way it thunders.
上次故事讲到 男孩摔下了山
Last we heard of him, the boy had fallen down.
他摔下了山 陷入深眠
He had fallen down the hill and into the deepest of sleeps.
但是故事并没有结束
But all was not lost.
他被一个老妪发现
He was discovered by an old woman.
老妪有一个鼓
She had a drum.
一个充满魔力的鼓 鼓声十分优美
A magic drum that beat so beautifully
鼓声唤醒了男孩
that his heart woke up.
她知道这个男孩一定有什么诉求 她便问男孩
She knew he must be on a quest, and so she asked him...
你在找什么？
What is it you seek?
你知道的 恐怖的象王派他的爪牙偷走了...
Well, you see, the dreadful Elephant King sent his jaguars to steal the...
没有人战胜过象王
No one has ever overcome the Elephant King.
- 我知道  - 那你凭什么认为你可以打败他？
- I know. - Well, what makes you think you can?
我必须战胜它
I need to.
我必须战胜它 仅此而已
I just need to, that's all.
这可不是个好答案
That's not a very good answer.
尽管如此 老妪还是告知他需要去寻找三件物品...
Nevertheless, the woman told him he'd need to find three things...
一件闪着光
something that shines,
一件用于抓捕的
something that ensnares,
一件能使人感到平静
and something that soothes.
只有集齐这三件事物 他才可以战胜象王
Only then would he overcome the Elephant King.
把它们都给我吧 拜托了
Give them to me, please!
我可没有
I don't have them,
你还是快去寻找它们
so you'd better go look for them.
要快哦 如果不及时播种 村民可就没有收成了
And hurry! If the seeds are not planted soon, there will be no harvest.
是的 我知道
Yes, I know.
她告诉男孩要去东边
She told him to head east.
那边才是东
East is the other way.
那个未知的东西一直尾随着男孩
Still something followed the boy,
而男孩还是不敢面对它
and still he could not face it.
- 他没收下钱？  - 我觉着贿赂他们没用
- He didn't take the money? - I don't think bribes work on them.
不不不 可能钱不够吧
No, no. It probably wasn't enough.
钱太少可能让他感到不爽
It might have insulted him.
你只需要再攒些钱 下次机灵点
You'll just have to save up more and be even smarter next time.
- 啊  - 你要我机灵点？
- Aaah! - I have to be smarter?
我听说有个人给杂工很高的薪水
I've heard there is a guy who pays well for small jobs.
跟我走
Come on.
先生您好 我们来找工作
Sir, we have come to work.
- 你们是？ - 我是德利瓦 这是奥狄什
- And you are? - I'm Deliwar. And this is Aatish.
他是我兄弟
We are brothers.
奥狄什算什么名字？
What kind of a name is Aatish?
我不知道 这要问我们的爸爸了
I don't know. Ask our father.
- 你爸在哪？ - 他在俄国人的枪下殉道了
- Where is your father? - He was martyred by the Russians.
只要价钱公道
We can do any job you want.
我们什么都能做
For the right price.
我想这应该是最后一个了吧
That's the last one, I think.
我们这是在哪？
Where are we anyway?
可算搬完了 你们这两个孩子真弱
About time. You boys are not very strong.
这可比你说的工作重多了
It was more work than you said.
这是你们的报酬 快走开吧
Here you are. Now be off.
嘿 我们可都是按你说的做的
Hey, we did all that you asked.
等等 你说过要把我们带回去的
Wait! You said you'd drive us back.
我可不是出租车司机 自己回家吧
I'm not a taxi. Make your own way home.
你们装货这么慢已经让我迟到了
I'm late already because you took so long to load the truck.
等等
Wait!
我得休息会
I need to rest a moment.
沿着路走 这个地方可能有地雷
Stay on the path. This place might be mined.
这点钱可不够 我们需要更好的工作
This is not nearly enough. We need better jobs.
- 比如呢？ - 我听说烧砖挣的钱挺多
- Like what? - I heard brick making pays well.
但会很累
But it's hard work.
真希望我能更强壮一些
I wish I was stronger.
可你不是有个哥哥吗？
But you have an older brother, don't you?
以前他总是让你骑在脖子上 带你去上学
He used to bring you to school on his shoulders.
他叫什么？
What's his name?
苏莱曼
Sulayman.
他已经去世了
He died.
什么原因？疾病？
How? Was it the sickness?
- 我不知道 - 可你妈妈应该跟你讲过吧
- I don't know. - But your mother must have told you.
她从没提起过 懂吗？
She doesn't speak of it. All right?
好吧
All right.
嘿 看看这个
Hey, look what I've got.
我在我爸爸的小收纳箱里发现的
I found it in a little box where my father keeps his things.
你能相信海水竟是如此的蓝吗？
Can you believe the water is that blue?
这真漂亮
It's very nice.
提供代写代读服务
Anything written! Anything read!
上次我没付钱
I didn't pay you last time.
- 该给你多少？ - 没关系的 呃...
- How much do I owe you? - It's okay. I...
怎么 坏消息就不收费吗？
What, you don't charge for bad news?
是谁教你识字的？那个残疾的老师吗？
Who taught you to read? The crippled teacher?
嗯 他是我叔叔
Yes. My uncle.
你写信跟读信一样厉害吗？
Can you write as good as you read?
我可以的
I can.
瞧
Here.
我觉得你可能会要回这封信 所以就一直留着呢
I kept this in case you wanted it.
告诉我 告诉我哪处是她的名字
Show me. Show me where it says her name.
哪写了“哈拉”
Where it says "Hala."
那儿 看到了吗？
There. See?
哈拉
Hala.
你知道哈拉是什么意思吗？
Do you know what it means?
不知道
No.
有时候 在你透过晴朗的夜空看月亮时
Sometimes, on a clear night when you look at the moon,
能看到月亮被一条明亮的光圈围绕着
you can see a bright outline around it.
那条光圈就叫作哈拉
That outline is called hala.
我妻子以它来取名
My wife was named for that light.
- 给你 - 这太多了
- Here. - This is too much.
别推辞
Don't argue with me.
谢谢你
Thank you.
好啦 扎西 我可以揪你的吗？
Stop it, Zaki. Can I pull yours?
让他安静点 我还想睡觉呢
Keep him quiet. I'm trying to sleep.
- 你犯什么毛病呢？ - 要不你给扎西讲个故事吧 好不好？
- What's the matter with you? - Why don't you tell Zaki a story, hmm?
我们都很喜欢
We'd all like that.
好吧 扎西 你想听故事里的小男孩后来怎么样了吗？
Well, Zaki, do you want to know what happened to the boy?
好的 好的 还有大象
Yes, yes, and the elephant.
男孩跑啊跑 他很害怕 心跳得特别快
The boy ran and ran, his heart beating fast in fear.
身后追逐他的东西丝毫没有停下的意思
And the thing that chased him never stopped.
于是小男孩非常害怕地躲在树后
So the boy hid behind a tree and he waited for courage.
一位老妇人想要挤山羊奶
An ancient woman had been trying to milk a goat,
可她后背酸痛难忍
but her back was very sore.
我的背好痛啊
My back is very sore.
男孩很同情老妇人 于是让老妇人在树荫下休息
The boy took pity on her and told her to rest under the shade of a tree
他来挤羊奶
and he would do the milking instead.
您到树荫下坐着吧
Please sit under the shade of this tree,
我来帮您挤
and I will do the milking instead.
当他挤完羊奶后
When he finished milking the goat,
老妇人与他分享美味又温暖的羊奶
the old woman shared the lovely, warm milk with him.
这是他喝过最好喝的羊奶
It was the nicest milk he had ever tasted,
于是他称赞老了妇人的羊群
and he complimented the woman on her goats.
您山羊的产奶量真多
Your goats are very generous.
老妇人给男孩一面镜子作为回报
In return, the old woman gave him a mirror.
看 多闪啊
See how it shines!
得到镜子后 男孩非常高兴
The boy was delighted with the mirror,
但他看着镜子时 镜子照出了尾随他的东西
but as he looked into it, he saw the reflection of the thing that followed him!
妈妈 你在做什么？
What are you doing, Mama-jan?
我在收拾苏拉娅的衣服
I'm laying out Soraya's good clothes.
这些衣服要我拿到市场去卖吗？
Am I to sell them at the market?
嘘 帕尔瓦娜 该睡觉了
Shh, shh, shh, Parvana. It's time to sleep.
我得想方设法去白沙瓦
I just need to find a way to get to Peshawar,
在那里我会计划出属于我的未来
and I can figure it out from there.
我想果阿会有海滩
I think there's a beach in Goa
那的游客非常富有
where the tourists are very rich.
如果他们有钱 那我的蓝色石头就能卖出去了
If they're rich, they would buy my blue stones,
在那我就能经营我的小生意了 届时你就可以跟我合伙干了
and that's where I'd set up my business, and you could join me.
在我找到爸爸后
Once I find Baba.
嗯 在你找到你爸爸后
Once you find your Baba.
85呗
I'll give you 85.
- 90最低 - 82怎么样
- Ninety. - Eighty-two.
最少85了
Eighty-five, and that's final.
再加上一串葡萄 就这么定了
Eighty-five and a bunch of grapes, and that's final.
你写字下笔太重了 但字写得不错
You're leaning too hard on the pen, but your writing is good.
如果你再温柔一点 写好字会更容易些
If you try it more gently, it'll be easier.
等等 请等一下
Wait! Wait a moment!
什么事？
What is it, child?
你曾问过我之前坐在我身边的那...那个老师的情况
You asked me before about the man who used to sit there... the teacher.
- 你叔叔？ - 他不是去了马扎里沙里夫
- Your uncle? - He didn't go to Mazar-e-Sharif.
我叔叔进了监狱 然而他是冤枉的
He was taken to prison. But he did nothing wrong.
- 哪一个？ - 什么哪一个？
- Which one? - What?
- 哪所监狱？ - 普利查西监狱
- Which prison? - Pul-e-Charkhi.
已经过了几个星期了 但仍就杳无音信
It's been weeks now, and my family has had no word of him.
星期三去监狱一趟吧
Go to the prison on Wednesday.
去找我表弟罗尚帮忙
Ask for Roshan. He's my cousin.
告诉他是拉扎克让你来的 他力所能及的话 就会帮你的
Tell him Razaq sent you and he will help you, if he can.
德利瓦
Deliwar!
照这样干下去 等我到海边的那天 我都变成风烛残年的老太太了
With work like this, I'll be an old woman by the time I get to the sea.
或是个老头儿
Or an old man.
你坐着休息下 我给你讲个故事
You sit and rest, Deliwar, and I'll tell you a story.
- 故事？ - 对呀
- A story? - Yes, a story.
在很久很久以前
One time in the deep past,
从前有一个小男孩 他要把怪物偷走的袋子带回到村里 袋子里装着的是十分珍贵的种子
there was a boy who had to return a stolen bag of precious seeds to his village.
是个喜剧吗 还是...悲剧呢？
Is it a happy story or a sad story?
你听完就知道了
Just wait and see.
男孩得知 必须集齐三件事物
The boy had been told he needed three things
才能战胜象王
in order to overcome the Elephant King...
一件闪着光 一件用来抓捕的 和...
something that shines, something that ensnares and something that...
喂 你们两个 过来
Hey, you two! Come here!
来啊
Come on!
我认识他
I know that boy.
快点 马上过来
Hurry up. Come here.
快点啊
Come on.
我们最好听他的话过去
We'd better do what we're told.
赶快啊 懒鬼
Get a move on, lazy kids.
这就是新来的苦力？
So these are the new workers?
快回答啊 你们是傻子吗？
Where are your tongues? Are you stupid?
伊德瑞斯提议用掰手腕的方式来做个小测验
Idrees suggested we have a little arm-wrestling match.
看看你们是否有资格为我工作
To see if you're strong enough to work for me.
我看到你坐在那儿偷懒
I saw you sitting down over there instead of working.
停下 伊德瑞斯
Idrees, stop now.
给我来杯茶水
Make me some tea.
小不点 让我见识下你有多废物
Let me see how feeble you are, little one.
这弱鸡连手都抬不起来
He can't even lift his hand.
起来吧 端点茶水来
Get up and make us tea.
叔叔 我觉得你需要招新工人了
Uncle, I think you need new workers.
- 这两个简直太废了 - 够了 伊德瑞斯
- These ones are no good. - Enough, Idrees.
别难为这些可怜的娃了
Leave the poor kids alone.
他们俩还是太嫩
They are a little undercooked.
我知道你
I know you.
你是那个老师的女...
You're the teacher's daugh...
伊德瑞斯
Idrees.
把枪拿回来
Bring the gun back!
我说了 把枪拿回来
I said bring the gun back!
伊德瑞斯
Idrees!
滚出来
Come out now!
给我滚出来
伊德瑞斯 战争已经开始了 我们要向西转移
Idrees, it has begun! We are moving west.
我们接到命令要立刻行动
We have been given orders to go immediately!
我知道你是谁
I know who you are!
你听见了吗？
Do you hear?
快上来 快
Get up here! Come on!
现在就上来 你个怂包
Right now! You little coward!
你不是想参战吗？ 现在你的机会来了
You want to fight? Now is your chance to fight!
做个男人吧
You become a man.
他走了
He's gone.
他要是回来了呢？
What if he comes back?
那只能算他运气好
He'd be lucky.
我们这是在哪？
Where are we?
我逃跑时候来过这里一次
I came here once when I ran away.
不知道是我身体长大了 还是进来的洞口变窄了
I think the way in has gotten smaller or I have gotten bigger.
这东西看起来有点历史了
It looks old.
我丢了一只鞋
I lost a shoe.
我帽子也丢了 可我觉得它就在外面
I lost my cap, although I think it's outside.
你为什么揍他？
Why did you hit him?
把我爸绑走的那伙人里有他一个
When they took my father, he was one of them.
再给我讲讲那个男孩吧
Tell me more about the boy.
什么男孩？
What boy?
故事里的那个男孩
The story boy.
男孩觉得很冷
The boy was cold.
虽然太阳挂在空中 他却感受不到一丝温暖
Though the sun burned in the sky, it gave no heat.
但是他有一个又大又暖的外套
But he had a warm hat and a big coat.
不 他没有
No, he didn't.
他已经发现三件事物中的一件了...
He had already found one of the three things...
一个闪光的镜子
a mirror that shone.
但是当他往镜子里看时 他看到了他身后的东西
But when he looked at it, he saw something behind him.
那东西很吓人 非常恐怖
Something scary. Something dreadful!
- 是一匹马 - 不 什沃吉亚 不是一匹马
- A horse! - No, Shauzia, not a horse.
是啊 就是一匹马
Yes, it was.
还是一匹非常老的马 走起路来骨头都咔哒咔哒响
And it was a very old horse whose bones clattered together when it walked.
这一点都不吓人
It wasn't scary at all.
好吧  看到老马的样子 男孩感到很难过 于是他喂了它一些干草
Fine. The boy felt sad for the old horse and fed him hay.
然后他们都过上了幸福的生活
And they all lived happily ever after.
我才讲到故事的一半 这不是结局
It's the middle of the story, not the end!
从一个石室的门里
From a door carved into the stone,
走出来一个胖子
out came a round man.
你竟然把我的干草浪费在一匹即将死去的老马身上
You wasted my hay on an old horse that will soon be dead!
胖子把男孩扔进了一口古井的深处
The round man threw the boy deep into the belly of an ancient well.
啊..
Aaah!
在井的底部有绿宝石
At the bottom of the well there were emeralds,
胖子想让男孩把绿宝石拿给他 作为男孩浪费干草的补偿
and the round man wanted them brought up to him as payment for the wasted hay.
你得把那些绿宝石拿给我
You will bring the emeralds to me.
- 他的名字是？ - 你问的是那个胖子的？
- What's his name? - The round man?
不是 是那个男孩的名字
No, the boy.
你不能光讲人家男孩的故事 不给人家起个名字
You can't have a story about a boy and not give him a name.
你不起我可要给他起名字了啊
Give him a name before I do.
苏莱曼
Sulayman.
他叫苏莱曼
His name is Sulayman.
这是个好名字
That's a good name.
苏莱曼倒在井的底部
Sulayman lay at the bottom of the well.
突然 他看到了几具骷髅
Suddenly, he could see skeletons.
一共3具骷髅 它们的骨手里都攥着一颗绿宝石
Three skeletons, each with an emerald clutched in its bony hands.
- 他大声呼救 - 救命
- He called out for help. - Help!
那匹可怜的老马从井口向下望着他
The poor old horse looked back at him from way above.
然后它做了一件很神奇的事情
But the horse did something extraordinary.
它发出了世界上所有种动物的叫声
He neighed with the voice of all the world's animals.
苏莱曼爬啊爬 终于爬到了井的顶部
Sulayman climbed up, up, all the way to the top,
然后他对救他一命的老马表示了感谢
and he thanked the horse for saving his life.
谢谢你救了我的命
Thank you for saving my life.
苏莱曼拿到了那三块宝石
Sulayman had just three emeralds with him...
于是他要求胖子用食物来换
And asked the round man for food in return.
他很饿
He was hungry.
但那胖子即卑鄙又很小气
But the round man was wicked and cheap.
他扔给了苏莱曼一个渔网 让他自己捕鱼吃
He threw a fishing net at Sulayman and he told him to get his own food.
- 这网正是苏莱曼所需之物 - 哈哈
- That was exactly what Sulayman needed. - Ha-ha!
那件用来抓捕的事物
Something that ensnares.
但在苏莱曼的离开后
But as Sulayman left,
三具骷髅的鬼魂从宝石里出来了
the ghosts of the three skeletons came out of the three emeralds
它们在胖子头上缠转盘旋 吓得胖子魂不附体
and swirled and twirled and scared the round man
用如此手段来向害他们丧命的胖子复仇
in frightful vengeance for having lost them their lives.
苏莱曼和那匹老马继续向山那边进发
Sulayman and the horse continued their journey toward the mountain,
但老马越走越慢了
but the horse was getting slower and slower.
它实在是太老了 需要休息
He needed to rest, being very, very old,
于是苏莱曼为它搭了一个帐篷
and so Sulayman made a shelter for the horse
然后让这匹马等他回来
and told him to wait for him.
那匹马有意阻止男孩...
The horse protested...
但苏莱曼知道 象王和它的爪牙
but Sulayman knew he had to face the Elephant King and the jaguars
他必须亲自去面对
all by himself.
我们会再见面的 老伙计
I will see you again, old horse.
说完他就一个人上路了
And so on he went alone.
明天是星期三
Tomorrow is Wednesday.
我要到监狱去了
I'm going back there, to the prison.
他们到时候会让我见我爸爸的
They'll have to let me see him then.
从现在开始 你就别出门了
From now on, you're staying inside.
- 那么做太危险了 - 不 妈妈
- It's much too dangerous. - No, Mama-jan.
- 我们会一起设法逃出来的 - “我们”？
- We manage all right out there. - "We"?
我和德利瓦 她也是个女孩 我们一起工作
Me and Deliwar. She's a girl too. We work together.
我们已经给我表兄写信了 让他们给你姐姐在马扎安排一门亲事
We've written to my cousin to arrange a marriage for your sister in Mazar
他们回信表示同意
They wrote back, and it was accepted.
后天会有人来把我们带走
Someone will come for us the day after tomorrow to take us away.
- 你以后不用再冒险去监狱了 - 什么？
- You don't need to do this anymore. - What?
这日子不能这么过
We can't go on like this.
- 我们不能靠你养活啊 - 为什么？
- We can't depend on you to keep us alive. - Why?
我现在挣的钱足够养家了
I provide for you just fine.
这不是一个孩子的工作
It's not the job of a child.
我们怎么能撇下爸爸离开
How can we leave without Baba?
每天你回家的时候 身上都带着伤口
Every day you come home with cuts and blisters.
每天你出去工作 我都不知能否看到你安然归来
Every day you go out there, and I don't know if I'll see you back again.
我不能连你也失去
I can't lose you too.
我不会去的
I'm not going.
爸爸会回来的 我们走了 家里就没人等他了
Baba could come back, and no one will be here waiting for him.
那我们要等多久
So how long should we wait?
等到他们发现你是女孩 然后也把你从我身边夺走吗？
Until you're found out and taken away from me?
等到我不得不把扎西送出去 来赚钱养家吗？
Until I have to send Zaki out to earn our keep?
在我们离开之前 让我去看看他吧
Let me go see him before we leave.
好让他知道我们要去的是哪
Let me tell him where we are going.
- 帕尔瓦娜 - 让我帮他把手杖带上
- Parvana! - Let me bring him his walking stick.
然后我就跟你走
Then I will go with you.
我会做一个好妹妹 一个好女儿
Then I will be a good sister and a good daughter.
我发誓
I promise.
我保证
听话 不要走
Please don't go.
听妈妈的吧  现在外面太危险了
Please, it is much too dangerous now.
妈妈 我走了
Mama-jan, I'm going.
宵禁之前我一定回来
I'll be back tonight before curfew.
- 不要 苏莱曼 - 妈妈
- No, Sulayman. - Mama-jan.
- 你赶不回来的 - 让她去吧
- You won't come back. - Let her go now.
让帕瓦尔娜去吧
Let Parvana go.
哦
Oh!
帕瓦尔娜
Parvana.
德利瓦
Deliwar!
你差点把我吓死
You frightened me half to death.
我一直在到处找你
I've been looking for you everywhere.
找我干嘛？想跟我一起去柴家商店干活吗？
Why? You want to work at the chai shop with me this morning?
- 不 我不行 - 嘿 你想给扎西弄些糖果吗？
- No, I can't. - Hey, you want some candy for Zaki?
明天我们就要离开喀布尔
We are leaving Kabul tomorrow.
你要离开我吗？
You are leaving me?
家里都安排好了 我也无能为力
It's been arranged. There's nothing I can do.
我姐姐就要去马札里沙里夫结婚了
My sister is getting married in Mazar-e-Sharif.
我还要再去一次监狱
I'm going back to the prison.
我找到了一个能帮我的人
I found someone who can help me,
而且我需要更多的钱来贿赂看守
and I need to get more money to bribe the guard.
今天是最后期限了
I'll need it today.
你只会挨更多拳头的 这个想法很愚蠢
You'll just get another punch in the guts. It's a stupid idea.
这次不会的
I won't let that happen this time.
- 我说了这个想法很愚蠢 - 求你了帮帮我吧
- I said it's a stupid idea. - Please help me.
你想让我怎么做？
What do you want me to do?
像你的儿童故事里那样 用魔法变出一些钱来给你吗？
Magic some money into your hand like in your kids' stories?
那是行不通的 帕瓦尔娜
It doesn't work like that, Parvana.
我帮不了你
I can't help you.
赶紧逃到马札里沙里夫 然后享受那美好的婚礼吧
Now run away to Mazar-e-Sharif and have a nice wedding party.
也许他们也会给你配个丈夫 你的麻烦就都不存在了
Maybe they'll find a husband for you too and your troubles will be over.
至少能挺到婚礼结束
Until after the wedding, at least.
你这个傻瓜
You fool!
德利瓦
Deliwar!
什沃吉亚
Shauzia.
和我们一起走吧
Come with us.
我不能
I can't.
我爸爸会一直追到马札然后杀了我的
My father would come all the way to Mazar to kill me.
我不能就这样离开喀布尔 帕瓦尔娜
I can't leave Kabul, Parvana, not like this.
- 这儿 拿着 - 我不能拿你的钱
- Here, take this. - I can't take your money.
你就拿着吧
Please take it.
去看你爸爸吧
Go and see your Baba.
告诉他 他有一个好女儿
Tell him that his daughter is a good daughter.
告诉他 德利瓦说的
Tell him that Deliwar said so.
嘿 德利瓦
Hey, Deliwar.
怎么了？
What?
20年后的今天 就在你之前提过的
I'll meet you at that beach you were talking about,
那片月亮牵引海水的沙滩上
where the moon pulls the water,
我等待和你再次相遇
我想那时我会认不出你来的 奥狄什
I don't think I'll recognize you then, Aatish.
好吧 那你可以优惠卖我些漂亮的蓝石头
Well, you can sell me some pretty blue stones for a great price.
后会有期
Until next time then.
Until next time.
真主保佑你 你是费特马吗？
Peace be upon you. Are you Fattema?
是的 我是费特马
Yes, I am Fattema.
我是你的二表哥 穆罕默德·阿卜杜尔派我从马柞过来
I am your second cousin. Mohammed Abdul sent me from Mazar.
叫上你的家人一起 我们现在就得走了
Gather your family. We must leave immediately.
不 你看 你不应该这么早就来的
No, you see, you weren't supposed to come so soon.
我儿子不在 我们必须等他回来
My son is away. We must wait for him to return.
仗马上就打过来了 你没听说吗？
There is a war coming. Have you not heard?
我们必须赶在他们封路之前离开
We have to leave now before they block the roads.
我们必须等到她回家 我得等我的女儿
We have to wait until she comes home. I have to wait for my daughter.
儿子？女儿？到底是哪一个？
Son? Daughter? Which is it?
收拾东西 我们现在就要出发
Gather your things. We are leaving now!
帕尔瓦娜回来前我是不会走的 我们必须等她回来
I'm not leaving without Parvana. We have to wait.
我带你走已经算你走运的了 老女人
Count yourself lucky I'm taking you, old woman.
这个女孩和那个孩子可更有价值
The girl and the baby are of more worth.
我这趟可不能白来
I didn't come all this way for nothing.
要是现在不走 我们就无法离开这里了
If we do not go now, we won't get out of here at all.
- 我的宝贝 把他给我 - 快跟我走
- My baby! Give him to me! - Let's go! Argh!
扎西 扎西
Zaki! Zaki!
把孩子给我 把他给我
Give me my baby. Give him to me!
- 不要 把他给我 - 放开 放开
- No! Give him to me! - Let go! Let go!
- 问安 孩子 - 问安
- Salaam, little one. - Salaam.
你带着一根老人的拐杖打算去哪？
Where are you going to with an old man's stick?
这是我爸爸的
It belongs to my Baba.
我要带给他 到监狱里
I'm taking it to him, to the prison.
我知道了
I see.
我们顺路
We're going that way.
把我的孩子给我
Give me my baby!
- 快跟我走 如果你还想要这孩子 就跟我走 - 扎西
- Let's go! If you want to keep the baby, come with me! - Zaki!
我女儿还在外面
My daughter is out there.
那你为什么会愚蠢到让她一个人出去呢？
Then what kind of fool are you to have sent her out alone?
上车 否则你今天可不止会失去一个孩子
Get in, or she won't be the only child you'll lose today!
不要...把我的孩子给我
Don't... Give me my baby!
叫这孩子别吵
Keep him quiet!
我求你了
I am begging you.
等等我的女儿
Wait for my daughter!
来吧 苏拉娅 我们得生火了
Come, Soraya. We must start a fire.
我找罗山
I am looking for Roshan.
嘿 我找罗山
Hey! I am looking for Roshan.
我找罗山 我找罗山
I am looking for Roshan. I am looking for Roshan.
- 开门  - 离门远一点 你这笨蛋
- Open the door! - Get away from the door, you stupid kid!
- 我找罗山  - 快滚
- I am looking for Roshan! - Get out of here!
- 我找罗山- 你是傻子吗？
- I am looking for Roshan! - Are you stupid?
- 我找罗山 - 闭嘴
- I am looking for Roshan. - Shut up!
你在这干什么呢？
What are you doing here?
没事了 他是我儿子
It's all right. He's my son.
里边需要你
You're wanted inside.
这个男孩欠一些管教
That boy needs some discipline.
那是我的事
That's my business.
我的真主啊 你来这干什么？
What in the name of the merciful are you doing here?
今天是星期三 我来找你的表弟罗山
It's Wednesday. I've come to meet your cousin Roshan.
那边已经开战了
There's a war started.
罗山已参战去了
Roshan has gone to fight.
我们被从城里带到监狱 来清除那些不愿为我们战斗的人
We've been brought from the city to clear the prison of anyone who won't fight for us.
- 那个老师... - 他还活着吗？
- The teacher... - Is he alive?
我不知道
I don't know.
那个老师是我的父亲 我是帕尔瓦纳 他的女儿
The teacher is my father. I am Parvana, his daughter.
救救他吧 求你了
Help him, please.
太阳下山前我还没回来的话 你就赶紧跑
If I'm not back before the sun has gone down, you run.
能跑多远就跑多远 千万不要停
Run as far away as you can from here and you keep on running.
日落之后你绝不能待在这里 你明白吗？
You can't stay here after sunset. Do you understand?
- 谢谢你 - 你明白了吗？
- Thank you. - Do you understand?
- 是的 - 在那之前 你先藏起来
- Yes. - Hide yourself until then.
从前有一个叫苏莱曼的男孩
Once there was a young boy called Sulayman.
他知道他命中注定要为人民服务
He knew his heart was fated to serve his people,
但他快没时间了
and he was running out of time.
谢谢你 太谢谢你了
Thank you. Thank you so much.
- 来吧 上车 - 我们得回去找我的女儿
- Come on! Get in the car. - We have to go back for my daughter.
我说了 赶紧过来
I said come here. Now!
我们不会跟你走的
We're not going with you.
妈妈？
Mama-jan?
你 过来 听不见我说话吗？
You, come now! Do you hear me?
让你过来你就过来
You come here like I told you to!
你现在就过来
You come now!
我们不会和你走的 你开车离开吧
We will not go with you. Just drive away from us.
上车 快上车
Get in the car. Get in the car now!
妈妈
Mama-jan!
苏莱曼 苏莱曼
Sulayman! Sulayman!
勇敢点 苏莱曼
Be brave, Sulayman.
快跑 苏拉娅
Run, Soraya.
- 现在带着扎西快跑  - 妈妈
- Take Zaki and run now! - Mama!
快走 一直跑
Go! Keep running!
你..让我们..走
You... let... us... go.
开门
Open the door.
你背着那个人干什么？
What are you doing with that?
他已经死了 我要把他和其他尸体放在一起 开门 让我过去
He's dead. I'm putting him with the others. Open the door. Let me through.
- 都快点走  - 站住
- Move, move, move, move, move! - Stop!
- 所有人 排成一行 - 站住
- Line up. All of you, all of you. - Stop!
我说了 站住
I said stop!
天快要黑了
It will be dark soon.
拉扎克
Razaq?
拉扎克？ 拉扎克？
Razaq? Razaq?
苏莱曼
Sulayman.
镜子可以反射光！
The mirror shines!
闪瞎那些怪物
Use it to blind the jaguars!
然后用网罩住他们
The net ensnares! Throw it over them!
哈
Hah!
拉扎克 拉扎克
Razaq. Razaq!
拉扎克 我来找我的父亲
Razaq! I have come for my father.
我来找我的父亲
I have come for my Baba!
把他放下来
Put him down!
我说了把他放下
I said put him down.
你了解现在的状况吗？
Do you see what is happening?
你把他带到哪里去？ 谁在外面？
Where are you taking him? Who's out there?
你就不能睁一只眼闭一只眼吗？
Look away, can't you?
现在这么乱 放过这个男人又能如何？
It is just one man. What does it matter?
走
Go.
Go!
走 除非你要杀了我
Go, unless you're going to kill me.
我会尖叫并诅咒你
I will scream and curse you
直到我用尽最后一口气
until the last breath leaves my body.
来吧
Go.
你疯了 疯了
You're crazy. Crazy.
你死在这都与我无关
You can die out here for all I care.
去死吧
Die.
苏莱曼
Sulayman.
我不是来杀你的
I have not come to kill you.
苏莱曼
Sulayman!
用你的故事让他平静下来
Soothe him with your story,
那个妈妈从没说起过的故事
the one that Mama-jan can't speak of.
告诉他
Tell him.
苏莱曼
Sulayman!
我叫苏莱曼
My name is Sulayman.
告诉他发生了什么
Tell him what happened.
告诉他你的故事
Tell him your story.
我叫苏莱曼
My name is Sulayman.
我的母亲是一个作家
My mother is a writer.
我父亲是一个老师
My father is a teacher.
我的妹妹们总在争吵
And my sisters always fight each other.
有天我在街上发现一个玩具
One day I found a toy on the street.
就把它捡了起来
I picked it up.
它爆炸了
It exploded.
我不记得后面发生了什么
I don't remember what happened after that
因为这就是结局
because it was the end.
起作用了 苏莱曼 继续讲 继续跟他讲
It's working, Sulayman! Tell him. Tell him!
我叫苏莱曼
My name is Sulayman.
我的母亲是一个作家
My mother is a writer.
我父亲是一个老师
My father is a teacher.
我的妹妹们总在争吵
And my sisters always fight each other.
有天我在街上发现一个玩具
One day I found a toy on the street.
就把它捡了起来
I picked it up.
它爆炸了
It exploded.
这就是结局
It was the end.
我叫苏莱曼
My name is Sulayman.
我的母亲是一个作家
My mother is a writer.
有天我在街上发现一个玩具
One day I found a toy on the street.
我父亲是一个老师
My father is a teacher.
- 我把它捡了起来 - 我的妹妹们总在争吵
- I picked it up. - And my sisters always fight each other.
它爆炸了
It exploded.
有天我在街上发现一个玩具
One day I found a toy on the street.
我不记得后面发生了什么
I don't remember what happened after that.
我把它捡了起来
I picked it up.
因为这就是结局
Because it was the end.
象王对男孩的态度发生了转变
The Elephant was transformed.
他从山峦中拿出那袋种子
He took the bag of seed from the center of the mountain
还给了苏莱曼
and gave it back to Sulayman.
苏莱曼回到他的家乡
Sulayman returned to his village.
村民们载歌载舞
There was much dancing and singing
开怀大吃
and laughing and eating.
拉扎克？
Razaq?
爸爸？
Baba?
爸爸  他还活着吗？
Baba! Is he alive?
这不是他的血 他还活着
It is not his blood. He lives.
离开这里 孩子 快走吧
Get out of here now, child. Go on.
全速离开此地
As fast as you can.
这是月亮
It's the moon.
苏拉娅
Soraya.
苏……拉娅
S... Sora... Soraya!
- 妈妈？ - 苏拉娅
- Mama? - Soraya!
苏……
So...
在我们家乡 人才是最无价的珍宝
We are a land whose people are its greatest treasure.
我们的家乡是在两个交战国的边境交汇处
We are at the edges of empires at war with each other.
帕尔……
Par...
帕尔瓦娜
Parvana.
我们的家园在兴都库什山脉的利爪下被分成数个部分
We are a fractured land in the claws of the Hindu Kush mountains,
有北部沙漠那炽烈之眼的灼热
scorched by the fiery eyes of the northern deserts.
亦包括那黑白交汇的冰峰之凛冽
Black rubble earth against ice peaks.
我们的家园叫阿里亚纳
We are Ariana,
是高尚之乡
the land of the noble.
话要说的更有道理 而不是提高音量
Raise your words, not your voice.
毕竟是雨水滋润花朵生长
It is rain that makes the flowers grow,
而不是雷鸣
not thunder.